<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>X. Capaldi - Personal Blog</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com</link>
<description>Posts from Xavier Capaldi. Use an RSS reader to receive notifications on new posts.</description>
<copyright>2021 Xavier Capaldi</copyright>
<language>en-us</language>
<item>
<title>KOH etch calculator</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com/posts/20200823-koh-calculator/index.html</link>
<description> In my microfabrication processes I often use KOH (potassium hydroxide/caustic potash/lye) to etch silicon and silicon dioxide. The etch rate is dependent on KOH concentration and the temperature of the solution. When working with delicate features, it is important to precisely control the etch.  A web-based etch calculator makes it much easier to set up in the wet lab. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Terminal Braid Knotting Model</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com/posts/20200515-tbkm/index.html</link>
<description> I wrote a script to generate (and analyze) knots with a terminal braid knotting model. Knot are drawn completely in the terminal using unicode box-drawing characters and as such, the raw data can be saved (and read) as text files. <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/104/42/16432">Raymer and Smith</a> originally proposed a similar knotting model to describe agitated knot formation. Knots form at the mobile end of an open string so their model involved a coiled chain where one end was able to move over or under adjacent strands randomly for each time step. This script extends their model and allows for varying crossing parameters and initial conditions. In addition, you can control limit which strands are accessible to the terminal end. It is quite easy to reproduce the results of Raymer and Smith but despite generating tens of thousands of knots with varying parameters, I wasn't able to glean any other useful information. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>ImageJ/FIJI plugins for background subtraction and stack operations</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com/posts/20200127-fiji-noise-subtract/index.html</link>
<description> <a href="https://fiji.sc/">Fiji</a> is a extended distribution of the open source <a href="https://imagej.net/Welcome">ImageJ</a> platform for scientific image analysis. It is an excellent tool for working with microscopy data. While the tool is written in Java, it is highly extensible through scripts which can be written in a variety of languages. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>An Apparatus Based on an Atomic Force Microscope for Implementing Tip-Controlled Local Breakdown</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com/posts/20191220-tclb-instrumentation/index.html</link>
<description> <b>Abstract:</b> Solid-state nanopores are powerful tools for sensing of single biomolecules in solution. Fabrication of solid-state nanopores is still challenging, however; in particular, new methods are needed to facilitate the integration of pores with larger nanofluidic and electronic device architectures. We have developed the tip-controlled local breakdown (TCLB) approach, in which an atomic force microscope (AFM) tip is brought into contact with a silicon nitride membrane that is placed onto an electrolyte reservoir. The application of a voltage bias at the AFM tip induces a dielectric breakdown that leads to the formation of a nanopore at the tip position. In this work, we report on the details of the apparatus used to fabricate nanopores using the TCLB method, and we demonstrate the formation of nanopores with smaller, more controlled diameters using a current limiting circuit that zeroes the voltage upon pore formation. Additionally, we demonstrate the capability of TCLB to fabricate pores aligned to embedded topographical features on the membranes. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Whyknot</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com/posts/20191204-whyknot/index.html</link>
<description>Whyknot </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nanopore Formation via Tip-Controlled Local Breakdown Using an Atomic Force Microscope</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com/posts/20190424-tclb/index.html</link>
<description> <b>Abstract:</b> The dielectric breakdown approach for forming nanopores has greatly accelerated the pace of research in solid‐state nanopore sensing, enabling inexpensive formation of nanopores via a bench top setup. Here the potential of tip‐controlled local breakdown (TCLB) to fabricate pores 100× faster, with high scalability and nanometer positioning precision using an atomic force microscope (AFM) is demonstrated. A conductive AFM tip is brought into contact with a silicon nitride membrane positioned above an electrolyte reservoir. Application of a voltage pulse at the tip leads to the formation of a single nanoscale pore. Pores are formed precisely at the tip position with a complete suppression of multiple pore formation. In addition, the approach greatly accelerates the electric breakdown process, leading to an average pore fabrication time on the order of 10 ms, at least two orders of magnitude shorter than achieved by classic dielectric breakdown approaches. With this fast pore writing speed over 300 pores can be fabricated in half an hour on the same membrane. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>On the Biomechanics of Cardiac S-Looping in the Chick: Insights from modeling and perturbation studies</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com/posts/20190327-cardiac-s-looping/index.html</link>
<description> <b>Abstract:</b> Cardiac looping is an important embryonic developmental stage where the primitive heart tube (HT) twists into a configuration that more closely resembles the mature heart. Improper looping leads to congenital defects. Using the chick embryo as the experimental model, we study cardiac s-looping wherein the primitive ventricle, which lay superior to the atrium, now assumes its definitive position inferior to it. This process results in a heart loop that is no longer planar with the inflow and outflow tracts now lying in adjacent planes. We investigate the biomechanics of s-looping and use modeling to understand the nonlinear and time-variant morphogenetic shape changes. We developed physical and finite element models and validated the models using perturbation studies. The results from experiments and models show how force actuators such as bending of the embryonic dorsal wall (cervical flexure), rotation around the body axis (embryo torsion), and HT growth interact to produce the heart loop. Using model-based and experimental data, we present an improved hypothesis for early cardiac s-looping. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>From 2D to 3D: Graphene molding for transparent and flexible probes</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com/posts/20190128-graphene-probes/index.html</link>
<description> <b>Abstract:</b> Chemical vapor deposition (CVD) has been widely adopted as the most scalable method to obtain single layer graphene. Incorporating CVD graphene in planar devices can be performed via well-established wet transfer methods or thermal adhesive release. Nevertheless, for applications involving 3D shapes, methods adopted for planar surfaces provide only a crude solution if a continuous, tear-free, wrinkle-free graphene layer is required. In this work, we present the fabrication and characterization of Polydimethylsiloxane-supported 3D graphene probes. To accommodate 3D geometries, we perform CVD on catalysts possessing a non-trivial 3D topology, serving to mold the grown graphene to a final non-trivial 3D shape. This advance overcomes challenges observed in standard transfer processes that can result in uneven coverage, wrinkles, and tears. To demonstrate the potential of our different transfer approach, we apply it to fabricate graphene electrical probes. Graphene, due to its flexibility, transparency, and conductivity, is an ideal material with which conventional metal based probes can be replaced. In particular, with a contact impedance on the order of 10 kΩ, our graphene probes may find applications, such as in electrophysiology studies. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Probing the Organization and Dynamics of Two DNA Chains Trapped in a Nanofluidic Cavity</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com/posts/20180906-2-dna-1-cavity/index.html</link>
<description> <b>Abstract:</b> Here we present a pneumatically-actuated nanofluidic platform that has the capability of dynamically controlling the confinement environment of macromolecules in solution. Using a principle familiar from classic devices based on soft-lithography, the system uses pneumatic pressure to deflect a thin nitride lid into a nanoslit, confining molecules in an array of cavities embedded in the slit. We use this system to quantify the interactions of multiple confined DNA chains, a key problem in polymer physics with important implications for nanofluidic device performance and DNA partitioning/organization in bacteria and the eukaryotes. In particular, we focus on the problem of two-chain confinement, using differential staining of the chains to independently assess the chain conformation, determine the degree of partitioning/mixing in the cavities and assess coupled diffusion of the chain center-of-mass positions. We find that confinement of more than one chain in the cavity can have a drastic impact on the polymer dynamics and conformation. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Masters Thesis</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com/posts/20180814-msc-thesis/index.html</link>
<description> <b>Abstract:</b> A pneumatically-actuated membrane device is designed and fabricated to dynamically confine multiple DNA chains into nanoscale pit features. A nanoscale nitride membrane is used as a lid that deflects under pneumatic pressure. With this device single λ-DNA and plasmid DNA are studied in a confined environment. In addition systems are studied containing two λ-DNA chains or a single λ-DNA with a plasmid. The interactions of multiple confined macromolecules were quantified, which is relevant in the study of biological systems in which multiple DNA molecules are highly confined by cell walls and other organelles. This confinement is found to greatly impact the polymer dynamics and molecule conformation. In addition preliminary work has been done to extend the device to map unstained molecules trapped under a membrane in fluorescent buffer. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Honors Thesis</title>
<link>http://www.xcapaldi.com/posts/20160426-honors-thesis/index.html</link>
<description> <b>Abstract:</b> Polymer crystallization is a complex process which is influenced by a variety of factors. Atomic force microscopy is used to explore the material properties of polymer crystals. Poly(ethylene-oxide) is used in a variety of molecular weights as the sample. In addition, a variety of sample preparation methods and microscopy modes were tested. A relatively new imaging technique was identified for the characterization of polymer crystals: amplitude modulation-frequency modulation viscoelastic mapping. This mode was used to measure material properties such as stiffness and dissipation. </description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>